To understand the differences and uses of appendChild and append in JavaScript, here’s a detailed explanation of each method:
appendChild Method
Description
The appendChild method is part of the Node interface and is used to add a node to the end of the list of child nodes of a specified parent node. Here are the key points:
Syntax: parentNode.appendChild(childNode);246
Parameters: The childNode is the node that will be appended to the parentNode246.
Return Value: The method returns the appended childNode. If the childNode is a DocumentFragment, it returns the empty DocumentFragment after its contents have been moved245.
Behavior:
If the childNode is an existing node in the document, it is moved from its current position to the new position345.
If the childNode is a DocumentFragment, its entire contents are moved into the child list of the specified parent node

EXAMPLES : 

<!-- Creating a new element and appending it -->
<div id="container"></div>
<script>
  const container = document.getElementById('container');
  const paragraph = document.createElement('p');
  paragraph.textContent = 'This is a new paragraph.';
  container.appendChild(paragraph);
</script>

<!-- Moving an existing element -->
<ul id="list1">
  <li>Item 1</li>
  <li>Item 2</li>
</ul>
<ul id="list2"></ul>
<script>
  const list1 = document.getElementById('list1');
  const list2 = document.getElementById('list2');
  const item = list1.firstElementChild;
  list2.appendChild(item);
</script>


Exceptions
HierarchyRequestError or DOMException can be thrown if the DOM constraints are violated, such as appending a node that would create a cycle or if the node is not a valid child for the parent


append Method

Description
The append method is part of the Element interface and is used to append one or more nodes or strings to the end of the list of child nodes of an element. Here are the key points:
Syntax: element.append(...nodesOrStrings);4
Parameters: Unlike appendChild, append can take multiple arguments, including nodes and strings.
Return Value: The append method does not return any value


Key Differences from appendChild
Multiple Arguments: append can handle multiple nodes or strings in a single call, whereas appendChild can only handle one node at a time34.
Strings: append can append strings directly, which will be treated as text nodes, whereas appendChild requires creating a text node explicitly


EXAMPLE : 

<div id="container"></div>
<script>
  const container = document.getElementById('container');
  container.append('This is a text node.', document.createElement('p'), 'And this is another text node.');
</script>



Summary
appendChild:
Appends a single node to the end of the parent's child nodes.
Returns the appended node.
Can move existing nodes within the document.
Part of the Node interface246.
append:
Appends one or more nodes or strings to the end of the parent's child nodes.
Does not return any value.
Part of the Element interface.
More flexible than appendChild as it can handle multiple arguments and strings directly


