Description
The removeChild method is part of the Node interface and is used to remove a child node from its parent node.
Syntax

parentNode.removeChild(childNode);


Parameters
childNode: The node to be removed from the parentNode.
Return Value
The method returns the removed childNode. If the childNode does not exist, it returns null146.
Behavior
Removes the specified childNode from the DOM but keeps it in memory if a reference is maintained. If no reference is kept, the node will be garbage collected after a short time.
Preserves any event listeners associated with the removed node135.
Exceptions
NotFoundError or DOMException: Thrown if the childNode is not a child of the parentNode.
TypeError: Thrown if the childNode is null

EXAMPLES : 

<div id="parent">
  <div id="child"></div>
</div>

<script>
  const parent = document.getElementById("parent");
  const child = document.getElementById("child");
  parent.removeChild(child);
</script>


To remove all child nodes from an element:

const element = document.getElementById("idOfParent");
while (element.firstChild) {
  element.removeChild(element.firstChild);
}





remove Method
Description
The remove method is a newer approach to remove an element from the DOM. It is part of the ChildNode interface and can be called directly on the node to be removed.


SYNTAX : 

node.remove();


Parameters
None. The method is called on the node itself.
Return Value
The method does not return any value.
Behavior
Removes the node from the DOM. Unlike removeChild, it does not require accessing the parent node.
Also keeps the node in memory if a reference is maintained, similar to removeChild


EXAMPLES : 


<div id="child"></div>

<script>
  const child = document.getElementById("child");
  child.remove();
</script>

To remove an element without needing to access its parent:

const node = document.getElementById("child");
if (node.parentNode) {
  node.remove();
}




Key Differences
Parent Node Access
removeChild: Requires access to the parent node to remove the child node.


parentNode.removeChild(childNode);

remove: Can be called directly on the node to be removed, without needing to access the parent node.

node.remove();



Syntax and Convenience
removeChild: More verbose as it requires referencing the parent node.
remove: More concise and easier to use, especially when you already have a reference to the node to be removed.
Compatibility
removeChild: Supported in all browsers, including older versions (DOM Level 1).
remove: Supported in modern browsers but may not be available in very old browsers.
When to Use Each
Use removeChild:
When you need to support older browsers.
When you need to remove multiple child nodes in a loop and already have a reference to the parent node.
When you want to explicitly handle the parent-child relationship.
Use remove:
For modern web development where browser support is not a concern.
When you want a more concise and straightforward way to remove a node.
When you already have a reference to the node and do not need to access its parent.
In summary, removeChild is a more traditional method that requires access to the parent node, while remove is a newer, more convenient method that can be called directly on the node to be removed.


